- Is he dead?
- Yes.
Yes, he's dead.
Then I am Emperor.
- Yes.
- Whee!
Sh!
You are Emperor.
Everything I ever dreamed of
has come true.
Emperor.
I am Emperor of Rome.
I feel sorry for him, don't you?
- No.
- No? Neither do I.
- Let's announce his death.
- Not yet.
We'll put out a bulletin saying
he's as well as can be expected.
- Considering he's dead!
- Yes.
Then we must find the will
It will be in his study.
Come!
What a mess!
He would never let anyone touch it,
that's why.
It will be here somewhere.
You look over there
and I'll look here.
(CLAUDIUS) Write no more,
Claudius Write no more.
Have you found it, Mother?.
- Well. what is it?.
- It looks like a history.
- Of what?.
- Of our family.
Does it mention me?
Where does it begin?
With the death of his last wife,
Messalina.
What does it say about me?
Be quiet! How can I tell
if you keep talking to me?
The frog pool wanted a king.
Jove sent them Old King Log.
I have been as deaf and blind
and wooden as a log.
My chief fault?
I have been too benevolent
I repaired the ruin
my predecessors spread.
I reconciled Rome and the world
to monarchy again.
By dulling the blade of tyranny,
I fell into great error.
By sharpening that blade
I might redeem that error.
Violent disorders call
for violent remedies
Yet I am, I must remember,
Old King Log.
I shall float inertly
in the stagnant pool
Let all the poisons
that lurk in the mud hatch out
Yes
Let all the poisons
that lurk in the mud hatch out
She did not please you, Caesar?.
No, I can see she did not.
It was a mistake having her here.
A beautiful woman though.
Yes. Beautiful woman. Whoever
marries her will be a fortunate man.
- She's married already.
- Really?.
To the drummer.
- And has three children.
- Oh, I envy him.
He tells me she's a shrew.
Then I envy him his nights,
but not his days.
In marriage, one can't
have one without the other.
You see, Caesar, how even vagabonds
and gypsies like those
recognise the virtues of marriage
and a family...life.
Caesar?. Are you well?.
Is something the matter?.
Let all the poisons
that lurk in the mud hatch out
If you will allow us, Caesar,
to raise once again
the subject of your remarrying?
There are so many good reasons
for it.
But, chiefly,
your children need a mother.
And Rome needs a mother. It's not
right for an Emperor to be alone.
Your Uncle Tiberius was alone.
It affected his mind.
It doesn't follow that because
your three marriages were a tragedy
your fourth shouldn't be a triumph.
I've given this matter
a great deal of thought,
and there's someone
I'd like to recommend.
- You never mentioned that.
- I thought of it today.
Caesar, the one woman in Rome
who would be a perfect wife
is Lollia Paulina.
Lollia Paulina?
Are you mad?
She's ideal
She's the daughter of an ex-consul
She's lost none of her looks
with age, and she's still childless,
so she'll be good for Britannicus
and Octavia. They need a mother.
That's more important than anything.
But she's the stupidest woman
in Rome.
The Emperor has had clever ones
that have done him little good.
She's an absurd choice.
She thinks of nothing but ornaments.
- The Emperor needs...
- A wife capable of helping him.
Caesar, I have submitted many names
in the past for your consideration.
I have been less than enthusiastic
about most of them.
That didn't prevent you
putting them forward.
It was not I who was to marry them.
One can recommend with
less enthusiasm than one marries.
- Caesar...
- As I was about to say, Caesar!
One name comes to me now
with all the force of divine revelation.
The lady has been
in front of us all the time -
so close, in fact
that we've not noticed her.
I refer to the Lady Agrippinilla.
The Lady Agrippinilla?! Are you mad?
She's the Emperor's niece!
The union would be incestuous.
The Senate wouldn't allow it.
A hundred years ago,
first cousins couldn't marry.
Now it's done all the time.
The Senate will agree.
Now, Caesar,
she's in every way suitable.
She's a woman of intelligence,
the daughter of Germanicus,
and she would bring with her
the grandson of Germanicus -
Nero, a boy worthy in every respect
of Imperial fortune.
But the Emperor loathes Nero!
A hideous boy.
You are speaking of the Emperor's
grand-nephew!
I speak the Emperor's own words!
And I'll go further.
His mother is the most corrupt woman
in Rome. Even Caligula said so!
How dare you? How dare you?
Narcissus, you may consider
our friendship at an end.
From this moment, at an end!
Caesar...
Caesar! I cannot support these
monstrous calumnies against her.
- Caesar...
- In my opinion...!
you niece is the finest woman
in Rome.
An Emperor should have a wife
who is both good looking,
and of outstanding intelligence.
She has both!
I beg you to consider her.
It would be the Lady Messalina
all over again.
Worse! The Lady Messalina
with brains.
That's a combination more deadly
than all the tribes of Germany.
And she'll soon want that son
of hers adopted into the family.
Caesar, Caesar, I beg you.
Caesar, an uncle does not marry
his niece.
The union will be incestuous
and the gods abominate incest.
It will bring ruin and destruction
on Rome.
Let all the poisons
that lurk in the mud...
hatch out.
Caesar?.
Let all the p-poisons
that lurk in the mud...
hatch out.
I will m-marry my niece.
B-bring her to me.
(KNOCKING)
Come in.
Well?.
He's agreed.
He has agreed.
He wants to see you.
- Now?.
- Yes.
It was so easy
I could hardly believe it.
He'll marry me?
He said he'd marry me?
Yes.
What did he say?.
"I will marry my niece.
Send her to me."
That's all?.
Nothing else? No arguments?
No opposition?
- Only from Narcissus.
- Ah.
- What did he say?.
- I shan't repeat it.
What does it matter?. He lost.
It was only sour grapes.
I'll sour all his grapes
before I'm done.
And Claudius? He said nothing
about my being his niece?
Nothing.
- Nothing about incest?.
- Nothing.
Perhaps he fancies the idea.
I wouldn't blame him.
I shan't like it though,
the thought of you in his bed.
I'm beginning to have regrets
already.
I found it hard, when it came to it,
to suggest you.
It didn't stop you though, did it?.
No.
Your ambition always burned
more brightly than your passion.
Have you ever found my passion
wanting?
No.
But in my case, passion and ambition
are beautifully combined...
aren't they?.
I'm beginning to have regrets
already.
My regrets are mounting.
- I hope when you're married...
- Don't be silly.
Oh, I've hurt you.
And I shouldn't have.
Don't worry. I'll make it up to you.
Now. Make it up to me now.
- He's waiting for me.
- It won't take long.
You see, for once, my passion
burns brighter than my ambition.
Hurry, then. I imagine his passion
is burning too...
and at his age,
the flames don't last very long.
(KNOCKING)
Uncle? Pallas tells me
you wanted to see me.
Yes.
He said that you had decided
to marry again.
Yes.
And that you had chosen me?
Would you like to marry me?
Oh, Uncle!
You have made me the happiest woman
in the world.
Yes, I thought I might.
How could you know that?.
How could you know that I've loved
and respected you all these years?
I just guessed it, my dear,
just guessed it.
I shall be such a good wife to you,
you'll see.
And I shall be a mother
to Britannicus and Octavia
just as I am to my own dear Nero.
They shall be to me
as if they were my own.
And there'll be more, why not?.
I'm still capable
of bearing children.
And you, such a vigorous man.
Such firm flesh.
Who would have thought it?.
You shall have more sons,
I promise you.
And more love
than you have ever had.
Yes.
Love, Uncle, such as you
have never known before.
Oh, it makes my head reel
to think of it.
Does it not worry you, my dear,
that you will be committing incest?.
Oh, but you've done that so many
times before, haven't you?
With your brother, Caligula?
We all did things then that
we might not otherwise have done.
That's true. That is true.
Only some of us did them more
willingly than others, didn't we?
I'm not blaming you.
I'm only asking.
Well. since you ask,
the answer is no.
Such incest would be technical only.
But if it disturbs you...
No, I'm teasing.
Please don't be offended.
As a matter of fact the q-question
of incest is somewhat academic.
- What does that mean?
- Beautiful as you are,
your body is of less interest to me
than your mind.
I'm marrying you for your head,
my dear, not your heart,
of which, I suspect,
you have very little.
Well. then, that suits me.
You're not the sort of lover
one dreams of.
Not the sort that you dream of.
Still. I won't discuss your dreams -
not on a full stomach.
I'm marrying you
because I'm tired of ruling alone.
There are many things an Emperor's
w=wife can do that others can't.
But I need a woman with a mind.
Does that appeal to you?
Admirably.
But I shan't be a cipher,
I can tell you that.
If you give me power,
I shall use it.
Now, why else do you imagine
I'm giving it to you?
- Well?.
- We are to be married.
- But why?.
- Why?.
He doesn't want me to share his bed.
He doesn't even like me.
He says he wants me
to help him rule.
- All the better.
- No, no. There's something odd.
What did he say
when you suggested me?
- I told you.
- Nothing more?
There was something.
It was nonsense.
What?. What did he say?.
Er... "Let all the poisons
that are in the mud hatch out"
or something like that.
Perhaps his mind's going.
Maybe he won't last long
after his marriage.
No.
We must keep him alive long enough
for my son to come of age.
Senators.
S-seven years ago, I undertook
the conquest of the island of Britain.
It has taken until now
to complete it.
One man and o-one man alone
has been responsible
for the enormous losses...
The war in Britain
finally came to an end,
and King Caractacus
was brought in chains to Rome.
The Senate called for his death
as punishment
for his long resistance to our arms,
but while his family cowered
before us, Caractacus did not.
I'll tell you this.
If the sword is all that you're
prepared to show us Britons,
then be prepared to carry it forever
in your hand...
and sleep with it forever
by your side at night!
For you will need it!
(APPLAUSE)
His courage and his dignity
won the hearts of the Senate.
He was granted a pension
and allowed to live in the city.
I'm near the end of my story.
I have been married
to Agrippinilla for five years..
and she has turned out
as loathsome as I thought she would.
As has that slimy son of hers.
His mother has plans for him.
She thinks I do not know,
but I do.
And I have my own plans
- He's very musical
- Yes.
I wonder, Britannicus,
that you don't take lessons.
I'm not interested in music.
Pity. You could play duets together.
That would be very unlikely,
Lucius Domitius being so gifted.
I wish you would stop addressing him
as Lucius Domitius.
He has adopted the name of Nero.
I forgot.
No, you do not forget.
I think you do it deliberately.
I tell you, I forget.
Well. you have been reminded,
which I think calls for a correction
and an apology.
- That isn't necessary, Mother.
- I think it is.
Well?.
I shall not apologise.
I think you will
Claudius, I insist
that you order him to apologise.
Apologise to N-Nero, Britannicus.
You've hurt his feelings
and you know how sensitive he is.
You side with them!
You take her side and his against me
all the time.
I shall not apologise!
You'll apologise
or you'll be punished.
What will you do? Have me executed
as you did my mother?.
I detest you all!
All of you!
I'm sorry to have been the cause
of that.
(AGRIPPILLINA) It's not your fault.
Nevertheless, I'll go and see him.
Come, Octavia, let's find your brother.
Perhaps we can pacify him.
I think you're very kind.
There's far too little kindness
in the world.
Have you noticed
how fond they are of each other?.
Everyone's commenting on it.
Nero simply adores her.
There's something I've been wanting
to speak to you about.
- Yes.
- It concerns the matter of...
- Pardon?
- The answer is yes.
You don't know
what I'm going to ask.
Aren't you going to suggest
that I marry Octavia to your son?
- Yes.
- The answer is yes.
Don't you wish to discuss it?.
What is there to discuss?
They’ll be well matched.
Nero's very fond you, you know?.
He thinks of you as a father.
He said to me
the other day, "I think of him..."
As a father.
Since he now will be marrying
Octavia...
The answer once again is yes.
Will you let me finish?!
You don't even know
what I'm going to say!
You're in your cups!
You've had too much wine again.
I thought you were going to suggest
I adopt Nero officially as my son.
Make him and Britannicus
joint heirs.
Of course, if that is not
what you were going to say.
Yes. Yes, it was.
It was. I just wish
you'd let me finish!
Your manner's very strange.
I just wanted to save
a lot of unnecessary discussion.
You see, that is the success
of our marriage, my dear.
I read your mind so quickly.
Think of the time it saves.
Goodnight.
Oh, put him to bed!
You should have consulted me!
I would have talked you out of it.
That's why I never discussed it.
Do you think that's right?. Am I not
your adviser on matters of state?
- Yes.
- Then why did you not consult me?
Do you think
that she doesn't consult Pallas?
No.
You know they’re lovers, don't you?
He's switched interests
from you to her?.
- Yes.
- Then why did you do it?.
Can't you see what you've done?
By marrying Nero to your daughter
and adopting him,
you've signed your death warrant.
Your wife has got everything
she wanted out of marrying you.
- She doesn't need you any more.
- I shall die soon anyway.
- How do you know?.
- Barbillus told me.
- He read my horoscope.
- You didn't need him to!
You've numbered your days more
accurately than a horoscope could!
Why did you do it?. Why?. Did you not
at least think of Britannicus?
I thought principally of him.
Then do you not see how this
will hurt him?
Do you know how you've hurt him
in the past?.
Yes, I know.
You realise, don't you,
you've numbered his days as well?.
Do you think they’ll let him live?
To say nothing of me!
What made you do it?. !
N-Nero is destined to rule after me,
not Britannicus.
It has been foretold, Narcissus,
nothing can alter it.
- Foretold? By who?
- By the Sibyl
Nero may become Emperor -
you've seen to that -
but your wife will rule through him,
as Livia ruled through Tiberius.
No. Nero will kill his mother.
That, too, has been foretold
by the Sibyl
What Sibyl?.
I've seen no such prophecy.
No. Nor has anyone now, except me.
Where did you find this?
It was given to me by Livia
j-just before she died.
She gave a birthday dinner.
She invited me. That was unusual
But her purpose became clear
later in the avenging.
She found this book
among Augustus' papers.
You won't understand it.
It's written in a very archaic language.
It frightened Augustus.
He kept it hidden.
Or perhaps he just didn't
understand it. But Livia did.
What does it prophesy?.
Among other things, it prophesied
Caligula's reign and his death.
It prophesied mine.
And it prophesises Nero's.
It is written, Narcissus.
Nothing you nor I can do will stop it.
Is that why you chose
the Lady Agrippinilla for your wife?
Yes. All my life I wanted to see
the Republic restored,
but I let myself be made an Emperor.
That was written too.
But I made a mistake.
I tried to rule wisely and justly,
reconciling people to the monarchy.
In doing that,
I was helping monarchy.
Now I shall destroy it
once and for all
Or rather Nero will destroy it.
He's as mad as my n-nephew, Caligula.
We're all mad, we Caesars.
When we are gone, the people will
finish with monarchies forever
and return to the sanity
of the Republic.
- And Britannicus?
- He is my instrument.
- He will restore the Republic.
- If he lives.
I have a plan that will save him,
but I must leave you
to make the arrangements.
Tell me what to do.
Well. let me rest for an hour,
then come to my bedroom
and we'll talk some more.
- Can I tell Britannicus?
- No, not yet.
- It grieves me to see you hurt him.
- Yes.
I killed his mother. I've been
less than a father to him ever since.
Now, I'm tired and I'm not well
- We must do it now.
- It won't be easy.
Narcissus watches him like a hawk.
Every morsel of food your husband
takes is tasted by someone else.
We shall need proper advice,
but that shouldn't be hard to get.
- Well. there is someone.
- Ah.
A woman. Locusta.
She's very skilled.
- I'll go and see her.
- Yes. But do it soon.
He's very unpredictable.
He's preferred my son to his own
at every turn. I don't understand it.
He could change his mind tomorrow.
Yes, it's strange.
It's very strange.
I feel he's playing some sort of game,
but I can't guess what it is.
Neither can I, but it worries me.
Remember that before Tiberius
struck at Sejanus
he raised him higher
than he'd ever been before.
There's something else
that worries me.
How sure are you of your son?
You may leave my son to me.
Even now that he's married?
I know you've had a great influence
on him, but he's no longer a child.
And when he's Emperor,
who will control him?
(KNOCKING)
- Who is it?.
- It is I, Mother.
Come in.
- Oh. It doesn't matter.
- No, no. I'm just going.
Lady.
(NERO) I don't like that Greek.
That Greek runs this Empire.
Do you have to receive him
in your bedroom?
- What is the matter with you?
- Nothing.
Why aren't you in bed?
Where is Octavia?
She's locked herself in her bedroom.
She won't let me in.
- Did you quarrel?.
- Yes.
- Why can't you sleep alone?
- I don't feel like it. I feel..
Oh, I don't know!
She won't lock me out when I'm Emperor
or tell me what to do. I shall do as I please.
It was very naughty of Octavia
to lock you out. Very naughty.
But she's only a child.
She doesn't understand how you feel
Would you like me to find
a pretty house girl for you?
Shall I find one
and send her to you?
- Is that man your lover?.
- No, of course not.
He's no business in your bedroom.
I won't allow it when I'm Emperor.
I won't see him here again.
Oh, my poor baby.
It's not fair, is it?.
Locking you out of your room.
And you the Emperor-elect.
But then, she's only your wife.
She doesn't feel for you
as a mother would.
A mother knows how her baby feels.
Yes.
She wouldn't let him be unhappy.
No.
Never.
Oh.
I'm so sleepy.
Senators, you see me here
for the last time.
I shall not come again.
This is in the nature
of a farewell speech.
(CRIES OF "NO")
No, no. I'm too old
and I'm not well enough.
I don't think you need my presence
here any more.
I sometimes wonder if you ever did.
(DISSENTING VOICES)
You know, the soldiers dragged me
from behind a curtain
and made me Emperor.
I n-never wanted it.
I think it was a mistake.
(LOUD CALLS) No! No!
Well. be that as it may.
Soon I shall retire behind another
curtain - the final one.
The one the gods draw over all
of us in the end, great and small
I shan't be sorry to see
that final curtain.
- May you live forever, Caesar!
- Oh, thank you!
But I've no wish to,
even if I could.
What you will s-say about me
when I'm gone...
I can only guess at.
I hope it won't be as cutting
as the things you've said while I was here.
Not to my face, of course.
That's not an Emperor's privilege.
But what is said about us
in our lives
is not always what history says.
And doubtless history will have
its say, as it always does.
And about that,
I have done something.
Not something
that need concern you...
but something.
You see, in the course of my life
I have known many people.
Great people. People who have
m-made Rome what she is today.
Yes. And one day,
they will all live again.
The dead will come to life.
The man who dwells by the pool
will open graves...
and deliver Rome up again.
She shall be seen
for what she truly was.
(FAINT CHEERING, GROWING LOUDER)
(SILENCE IN SENATE)
(ROAR OF A CROWD)
Well done, Claudius.
Emperor after all
Who would have thought it, eh?
You're a fool. boy, you always were.
People say it's not your fault,
but if it's not your fault,
whose fault is it, eh?
And your nose is still running,
Claudius. It's still running.
Excuse me.
Just a minute. Just wait your turn.
Shall a doctor be brought?.
It wasn't worth it, was it?.
I could have told you that.
Uncle Claudius, I wasn't the Messiah
after all Would you believe it?.
You could have knocked me over
with a feather when they told me.
Senators, let us continue
with the business of the day.
Leave us, Narcissus.
I will send for you.
- Father, you wanted to see me.
- Yes, come here.
My son, I've something very important
to tell you, so listen carefully.
No one must know. That's why
I've sent for you at this hour,
so no one in the palace
will know we've been talking.
Now, I intend to alter my will
in favour of Nero
and I want to explain to you
why I'm doing so.
- That's very considerate.
- Britannicus...
Why this sudden need to explain?
You haven't felt it before.
You adopted him,
you married him to my sister,
you made him Consul-elect and City
Warden without one word to me.
- You owe me nothing.
- Don't say that.
That's nothing to what I could say!
I may be only a child,
but I'm not blind and I'm not a stone.
I've seen how you preferred him to me.
It was for a reason.
You've never loved me.
You've never been as a father to me.
Never!
Time without number you've shown
the world what you thought of me
and I shall never
forgive you for it, never!
And you killed my mother!
I shall never forgive you
for that either. I hate you.
Now, you listen to me.
Yes, it's true.
For a long time after I discovered
what your mother had been...
how she had deceived me
every day of her life,
I could not find it in my heart
to love you.
But you must understand,
you must be a man.
Try to understand
a father's weaknesses.
I don't believe you are my son.
I believe you are C-Caligula's son.
But what difference does that make?
You do not have his nature.
I tell you this only to explain
why I could not find it in my heart to love you.
Was it my fault, then,
whose son I was?
Was I to be punished?
Does a child choose his parents?
Now, don't cry. Britannicus, please.
- May I go now?.
- No. Come here.
- Please may I go?
- Come here. Come here.
Come.
Oh, Father! Father!
I have something very important
to tell you, so listen.
First, no matter who your father
may have been, you are now my son
and I love you
more than anyone in the world.
- But Nero is destined to follow me.
- Why?.
Don't argue! It is written.
Nothing can alter it!
When I am gone, he will try to kill you,
as C-Caligula killed Gemellus.
That is why I have treated you
as I have.
Kept you out of the public aye.
I have a plan to save you.
Narcissus has arranged it all
through Caractacus.
The world is now wholly Roman.
There is nowhere you can be safe,
except the remotest part of Britain.
Nero will not be able to touch you there,
for there is no one to give you up.
Soon I shall allow
some of Caractacus' young men
to return to northern Britain,
and you will go with them.
You will stay
with Queen Cartimandua.
Only she and Caractacus' son
will know your identity.
She will send you north into regions
where no Roman's foot has ever trod,
- and there you will wait.
- Please...
Nero is mad.
He will destroy the Empire.
His excesses will demand a Republic
and you will return to restore it.
The Republic will live again.
No. No, I won't do it.
It's not honourable.
- Britannicus...
- No!
Do you think that I, a Claudian,
will paint my face blue
and go and hide among barbarians?
- There's no shame.
- No, I won't do it!
I'm not afraid of Nero.
Nero is a coward.
I can protect myself.
Let me put on my manly gown.
Once I'm officially a man,
I'll match Nero in everything he does.
I don't believe in the Republic.
No one believes
in the Republic any more.
No one does except you.
You're old, Father,
and out of touch.
I want my chance to rule,
and rule Rome as it should be ruled.
If you love me, give me that chance.
Yes.
Yes, I should have known
that would be your answer.
Well. so be it.
I've done all I could.
You shall have your wish.
May the gods protect you.
Britannicus.
Perhaps you will confound
the prophecies. Yes. Perhaps you will
Write no more, Claudius
Write no more.
I have told it all,
as I said I would,
and as the Sibyl prophesied.
I have told the truth.
I have set the record straight
it is all here
for remote posterity.
Come, Death,
and draw the final curtain.
I am tired.
Oh so tired.
So much for posterity.
Where's the rest of it?.
It must be here. Find it!
This looks like them.
Yes, this is them all right.
What a Herculean labour!
It must have taken him years.
Years. We'll burn the lot.
All that work? Good grief.
We must find the will
What a pretty thing a fire is.
(BRITANNICUS) Did they murder him?
(NARCISSUS) Yes.
Yes, they poisoned him.
But how?. How did they do it?.
Why didn't you protect him?
Oh, they were clever, very clever.
They tried to tamper with his food
and get at the slaves who prepared it,
but I always stopped them. Always.
I built a wall around him
they couldn't breach.
How, then, did she do it?.
I will tell you.
For I see now how it was done.
Unable to poison his food,
she must have poisoned her own.
Yes. Poisoned hers or part of it.
It was in a dish of mushrooms,
which he loved,
and out of which she'd been eating.
He'd finished his own
and was calling for some more.
It was then that she offered him
hers out of her own dish.
At first, I thought nothing of it.
When you see someone
eat from a dish,
it doesn't occur to you it may
contain something in just one part.
And then she lifted the mushroom
onto her fork
and held it out for him to take.
I knew then there was something
different about it.
I knew, as certainly as I had
ever known anything,
that he was suddenly
in the gravest danger.
And I knew too,
as certainly as I knew that...
that he knew - knew it was poisoned,
knew that his end was there
on that fork...
and that he didn't care...
that he welcomed it.
He died in the night, alone.
I knocked on his door soon after
dinner, but he sent me away.
I believe he wanted no one
to see him die.
You must go away.
They will kill you.
- No, I shall stay.
- Go now.
I have put on my manly gown.
I can take care of myself.
Poor Father. He never could.
Oh, I don't know. He didn't do badly
when you come to think of it.
(WOMAN'S VOICE)
Well, Old King Log?
The poisons all hatched out?
- Is that you, Sibyl?.
- Yes it's me.
- Where are you?
- Here.
(HE CHUCKLES)
Why are you laughing?
I cheated them again.
They all think I'm dead.
But you are dead, you fool!
You're as dead as anyone can be.
Oh, well. you can't survive
them all
No, not even you.
it's time to go.
Wait. Britannicus.
What will happen to him?
Nero will kill him.
- And Narcissus?
- Agrippinilla will kill him.
Then Nero will kill her.
It all sounds depressingly familiar.
- Yes Isn't it?
- And the Empire?
Oh that will go on,
as Livia said it would.
But they'll be no more Claudians
after Nero. He'll be the last.
But the Emperors won't be a had lot
after him.
Well, give or take a few..
Quite a story, wasn't it?
All of it
(THEY CHUCKLE)
Lucky for you
you made a copy and buried it.
it's time to go, Claudius
The ferryman is waiting.
- Just one thing more.
- You can't put it off..
You can't stay here forever..
No, I suppose not.
Now...
Close your eyes
it's but a short step to the boat,
a short pull across the river..
And then?
And then, I promise you, you'll
dream a different story altogether..
Farewell, Tiberius Claudius Drusus
Nero Germanicus
God of the Britons,
one-time Emperor of the Roman world.
Farewell.
Vtg